A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Study Group on Southern Africa, Consultant Files of Milfred Fierce FA1834
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Study Group on Southern Africa, Consultant Files of Milfred Fierce
1960-1989
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Fierce, Milfred C. (1937-2023)
FA1834
2.66 Cubic Feet 7 letter size document boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2021 and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2021:071.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
Collection consists of one series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Trips and meetings files, 1960-1989
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the files Milfred Fierce created when he worked as a consultant for the Ford Foundation's Study Group on Southern Africa. Ford established the Study Group to keep current on the developing situation in South Africa and the surrounding Southern Africa region during the second half of the 1980s. The Study Group continued the examination of Southern Africa done by the Study Commission on U.S. Policy towards Southern Africa funded by the Rockefeller Foundation and chaired by Ford Foundation President Franklin Thomas. The Commission produced the South Africa: Time Running Out report (SATRO) in 1981. Fierce was the Research Director for the Commission and would go on to be a consulting editor for the South Africa UPDATE Series to SATRO after his time with the Foundation's Study Group.
The collection consists of one series of trips and meetings files, documenting Fierce's travels to and meetings in South Africa, Zimbabwe, Zambia, Namibia, the United Kingdom, and other countries with Franklin Thomas and other members of the Study Group as well as the Study's Group's briefings in New York. There are also some documents pertaining to the development and activities of the preceding Study Commission on U.S. Policy towards Southern Africa from between 1979 and 1980.
Materials show the Study Group's interest in South Africa politics and the Apartheid system, anti-apartheid movements, Black leadership in South Africa, human rights and conditions of Blacks in South Africa, labor in South Africa, the South African economy and international corporations in South Africa, economic sanctions, disinvestment, and boycotts in relation to South Africa, the role of religion in South Africa, United States perceptions of and foreign policy towards South Africa, United Kingdom policy towards South Africa, and South African relations to other countries in the Southern African region, particularly Black led states.
Common material formats found throughout the collection include correspondence, notes, memos, drafts, reports, news articles, meeting materials, and travel documents like itineraries.
It is important to note that materials in the collection will sometimes use South Africa while referring to the broader region of Southern African countries.
Ford Foundation; Africa, Southern; Great Britain; Namibia; South Africa; Zambia; Zimbabwe; Apartheid; Rockefeller Foundation; South Africa -- Economic conditions -- 1961-1991; South Africa -- Foreign relations -- United States
- Trips and meetings files, 1960-1989; 1; 2.66 Cubic Feet 7 letter size document boxes
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains trips and meetings files Milfred Fierce created and maintained when he worked as a consultant for the Ford Foundation's Study Group on Southern Africa. It also includes some records from his time as Research Director for the Study Commission on U.S. Policy Towards Southern Africa which preceded the Study Group.
  Correspondence, notes, itineraries, invitations, meeting materials, and other items document Fierce's travels with Ford Foundation President Franklin Thomas and other Study Group members to countries like South Africa, Zimbabwe, Namibia, Zambia, and the United Kingdom. During these trips, Fierce and the Study Group met with individuals in government, academia, business, religion, and anti-apartheid movements such as Bishop Desmond Tutu. The Study Group's analysis of its investigation into ongoing developments in South Africa are represented in various drafts of its key findings found throughout the series. Other files document the Study Group's briefings on its objectives and work.
  The Study Group's investigation of South Africa's political, economic, and social landscape during the latter part of the 1980s focused on:
  - The administration of President P.W. Botha and the Apartheid system
  - Anti-apartheid movements
  - Black leadership
  - Human rights and conditions of Black South Africans
  - Labor
  - International corporations and their work in or policies towards South Africa like Barclays Bank
  - International perceptions of South Africa and the foreign policy of nations like the U.S. and the U.K towards South Africa
  - Economic means of opposing the Apartheid regime such as sanctions, disinvestment, and boycotts
  - Religion and religious groups' opposition to Apartheid
  - Relations between South Africa and other nations in the Southern Africa region, particularly Black led countries
  There are also some records in the series that show the Ford Foundation's grant activities in the Southern Africa region, particularly the countries of South Africa and Zimbabwe. These materials include recommended grant actions related to areas liked education and a proposal for the establishment of the Foundation's Harare, Zimbabwe Office.
  - African American Institute (AAI) African American Conference - Lusaka, Zambia, 1985-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Harare, Zimbabwe and South Africa 1989 trip, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Great Britain, South Africa, and Brazil 1986 trip, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - South Africa July 1985 trip - Franklin Thomas notes, circa 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - South Africa July 1985 trip (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - South Africa July 1985 trip - Materials collected (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - London, England July 1985 trip - Correspondence and briefing material, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - London, England, South Africa, Zambia, and Namibia July 1985 trip - Key points, notes, and impressions (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Lusaka, Zambia January 1989 trip (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - London, England and South Africa May-June 1987 trip (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Zimbabwe - Background and Ford Foundation work, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - South Africa 1986 trip, 1981-1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - London, England, South Africa, Zambia, and Namibia July 1985 trip - Notes (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
  - South Africa 1985 trip - Notes (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - South Africa trip notes January-February 1980 book 1 (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - South Africa trip notes January-February 1980 book 2 (Box 3, Folder 21-22)
  - South Africa trip notes January-February 1980 book 3 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Background materials for South Africa 1979-1980 trip, circa 1960-1980 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - South Africa trip book October-November 1980, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - South Africa trip book January-February 1980, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 26-27)
  - Background Study Commission on U.S. Policy Towards Southern Africa Meetings September-December 1979, New York City, New York (Box 5, Folder 28-29)
  - Study Commission on U.S. Policy Towards Southern Africa Feasibility Study - Recommendations to the Rockefeller Foundation, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Study Group Briefing literature May 1986, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 31-32)
  - Study Group Briefing May 1986 (Box 6, Folder 33-34)
  - Study Group Briefing May 1987, Tarrytown, New York, 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 35-36)
  - South Africa and Zimbabwe trips - Briefing materials, 1980-1982 (Box 6, Folder 37-38)
  - Study Group Briefing May 1987, Tarrytown, New York, 1986-1987 (Box 7, Folder 39-40)
  - Study Group Southern Africa July 1985 trip - Briefing book, 1982-1985 (Box 7, Folder 41-42)